okay we're gonna try a new meditation
this morning okay since you're already
expert about helping yourself in the
afternoon by the way use that afternoon
tongue man okay use it it helps a lot
alright and everybody has hard days
right and you in the morning you you
have to meet your ex-boyfriend or
something it's it's stressful so you can
prepare in the morning okay all right so
there's two classic ways to get
bodhichitta right and one is Tumlin and
then one is well sorry
one is exchanging yourself and others
and one is the mother meditation okay
then there's a famous text which is in
your reading who did
yeah I found the text I I was at when I
used to debate in the monastery then
once a year we have a competition with
the other monasteries and that
competition rotates to the six major
some couple monasteries saram a synergy
table among law something Gundam jumped
a shard say these are the six great
colleges so each big monastery has two
colleges and so we rotate the debates
and when I would go to gan dan monastery
which is about 12 hour drive if you go
in an American Road it will take an hour
I'm not kidding it's about a too hard
you have to drive around all the cows
and the pigs and I would stay at TGI
represents home which is the person who
made the poster the teacher of the last
time so I would stay at his home and he
was reborn as a young boy and but all of
his old assistants were still there and
he was a great book collector so I used
to dig around in his books and I found
this book in his books and I found many
great books there and so and I found a
nice picture of him with the Pope which
I'll show you sometime it's very cool he
had a long meeting with the Pope and
then this is a text I I actually don't
know who is the author but it's kind of
amazing and I found it in his
personal papers threat and they let me
dig around and this is a combined
meditation of the mother meditation and
exchanging yourself and other meditation
so let's test drive it let's see how it
goes okay and I'm not sure how it's
gonna go but if he had it in his
personal papers it's probably pretty
cool okay so let's try it out okay so
you are the first guinea pig you are the
first we are investigating this
meditation
let's try so relax your fingers and
relax her eyelids it's it's kind of hard
to relax your eyelids you have to try
small smile and pull in your stomach
slightly shoulders go back your
shoulders go together don't forget you
have option to look up over the horizon
with your eyes
and then please come to your breath
long exhales extra exhale John Brady
talked about it yesterday in his yoga
class I think it was count of 10 out
count of 6 in but extra exhale
then I'd like it to choose someone that
you know of or her know who is having
some problems right now and that's
actually we're going to go through 13
different steps in this meditation and
the first one is to be fair in your
choice of people who are having a
problem so we tend to we tend to worry
more about the people who are close to
us and we tend to ignore people who are
farther away from us and we don't know
them so much so
first job in Atonement meditation is to
choose a person who's having problem so
you might think about the people you
usually choose is someone it's it's
often someone you like or someone who is
close to you and here in the first step
we might today let's try Tumlin on
somebody
we don't know that well or maybe someone
we don't even like that much but
everybody has problems so so maybe we
can do Talman for someone in in syria
who's being bombed right now could be
someone in this class and we're not so
close to them but we know they have some
problem could be someone who had
some grief a relative passed away one
student in this class flew here from
China to Los Angeles and one of their
parents passed away and they got to Los
Angeles and they bought a ticket and
went home
so people we don't know well we don't
know very well choose someone but maybe
today for the Tong man choose someone
who's not that close or even someone we
don't like very much
and let's do something on them let's
take away their problem here we go
choose a person without prejudice
the second step of this combined but
each other meditation is to think about
how this person that were meditating
about has been our mother in one of our
past lives countless past alliances so
think about that this person that we may
not know very well maybe they don't even
have a name for us but let's understand
that they have been your mother as close
as your mother in this life everyone
around you has been your mother as close
as your mother in this life
third step is to try to think about all
the nice things they did for us in our
past life as her mom they risked their
life to give you life they carried you
for nine months they got sick they got
tired they had to think for nine months
about birth and if it's a former life
it's possible that birth was very
dangerous even now this can be very
dangerous so that person that you are
meditating about they were willing to
die for you before they met you and then
they taught you everything how to talk
how to eat how to walk how to make a
living how to go to school how to read
how to speak then think about all the
things that this person did for you
you're gonna have to keep the person in
mind and then you're gonna have to think
logically what they did for you in the
past lawyer
the fourth step of the 13 is to decide
oh I should pay them back I I would be a
strange person if I don't pay my mother
back for all the things she did for me
so this person that you're meditating
about think about paying them back for
all the kindness they gave us when when
they were our mum
now I switch to the other system and we
think this person that I'm meditating on
in me we have equal right to be happy
and I should work equally for their
happiness whatever effort I make to make
money for myself or feed myself or make
sure I'm happy I should also be making
the same effort for them we have equal
right to happiness all the people around
me have equal right to be happy I it's
not fair if I work harder on my own
happiness then I work on their happiness
here we go
step number six I could go on the way
I've been doing it I I could go on
taking more care of myself and not
taking so much care of this person who I
don't really know that well but if I do
that then something is wrong in the
world if I treat myself better than I
treat this other person then something
is going to be wrong all my happiness
comes from taking care of other people
so if I take care of myself more it's
going to do something to my happiness
over many years time over the length of
my life if I take care of myself more
and I don't worry about this person that
much then something would be wrong so my
happiness in my life over my life comes
from taking care of other people so if I
don't worry about this person very much
if I don't try to take care of them if
I'm prejudiced
if I take care of myself more then
something's gonna happen in my life my
life will get worse and worse my life
will be more and more unhappy so it's
even in my own interest to take care of
them more and more and don't worry so
much about myself okay here we go
step number seven there's a logic to
helping other people if I help this
person who I wasn't so interested in
before but if I put some effort into
helping this person if karma is true
then actually I will get more and more
things that I want so it's a win-win
instead of ignoring them and taking care
of myself which is a lose-lose situation
if I relax and happily spend some time
taking care of them then if karma is
true things will come to me happiness
will come to me so I made them happy and
I made me happy so it's a win-win if I
focus more on these other people and a
little bit less think about what I want
I will get more and more of things I
never dreamed of because karma grows
let's think about that
step eight in this meditation is to
think about what would happen in this
world if everybody thought like this if
everyone took care of other people
equally and if karma is true then this
world could be a truly healthy place so
it's the most beautiful thing we can do
to create happiness in this world is to
take care of other people maybe
especially the ones we don't know very
well or we don't like them so much
think about how right it is to follow
these laws of karma and take care of
everyone equally and have such a
beautiful result in our world if we all
did it
then step 9 we're gonna start exchanging
myself and others and I try to imagine
how people see me how does this person
see me so I put myself in their body I
put my mind in their body and I look at
me and how does it how do I feel to them
how did they see me I see them as
someone I don't know very well there's
someone I don't maybe I don't like them
that much but let's put our mind in
their body and let's look at me and see
how it feels especially how does it feel
that Michael doesn't treat me equally
and Michael seems to be more worried
about his own happiness thing about my
happiness how does that appeal to other
people
put yourself in their body and look at
you
now let's think about some what's
hurting them and what problems they have
and I want to take away their pain maybe
one of their main sufferings is thinking
about how we don't love them or we're
ignoring them maybe that's a one of
their the most painful things in their
life so now we're gonna start the actual
atonement
imagine that darkness in their heart and
maybe that darkness is how bad it feels
to them when they realize we don't
really care about them very much and
let's imagine that pain small pain in
their heart as a black small black cloud
oh Michael Casey Michael doesn't really
care about me as much as he cares about
himself and that hurts to to realize
that let's collect that black smoke in
their heart
now let's imagine a beautiful pink Lotus
in our own heart fragrance saw lovely
and in the center of the Lord is a
beautiful diamond you can imagine that
diamond ring with that diamond rod
diamond sparkling powerful and let's
take the black smoke out of our friend
and bring it to this diamond it exploded
and so start breathing we're gonna
breathe through both nostrils today your
in-breath is like a pump and it's
bringing the darkness out of their heart
oh it's I don't want you to feel that
sadness of being ignored by Geshe
Michael I want to take it away from you
even if it means I will have that
sadness I I don't want you to keep it
so each breath you take in more and more
darkness comes out of their nose out of
their body as soon as that leaves their
nose they start to feel happier and they
don't really know why secret I'm doing
secret taking away their trouble taking
away their heartache I bring this
darkness to the front of my own nose
and I get ready to take it away and I'll
count to three one two and three breathe
in the darkness comes down my throat and
touches the diamond in the Lotus there's
a bright flash of light destroys it
completely at that moment they feel so
happy oh all that trouble all that pain
in their heart that people are ignoring
me people don't really care about my
happiness it's gone then immediately
let's start sending golden light from my
two nostrils this is we're up to eleven
okay we're up to step 11 and I will send
into your heart the knowledge that
Michael loves you and Michael cares
about you Michael
admits his old mistake and now he's
going to treat you equally to other
people and equal to himself he's going
to give you the same kind of love he
gets to other people and even the kind
of love he gives to himself lots of
golden light
step 12 of the 13 steps we think about
if I have to take care of everyone the
same that I take care of myself that's a
lot of work that's a lot of trouble
that's gonna take a lot of time a lot of
attention I'm just one person and the
world is a big place and there are many
many people need my help I can say I
will treat them equally but it seems so
difficult and step 12 is to make a
decision in your own heart I figured out
I will take care of it it's like a mom
who has a bunch of kids and they all
need things and she doesn't have much
money but she doesn't give up and she
doesn't say I can't do it I'll find a
way I will find it I will take care of
it uh it's hard I'm tired I have a lot
to do there's a lot of people who need
me I will find a way to take care of all
of them I will work really hard I will
not give up that responsibility I will I
will take care of everyone somehow I
will take care of it I I will try I
don't give up and I don't avoid this
responsibility I will take care of
everyone who needs me
then the last step which is 13 which is
actually bodhichitta one of the best
ways to take care of other people is to
be a good example if i'm a joyful person
happy person even when I have problems
I'm tired and I have too much to do but
if I stay cheerful a big smile on my
face and always have time for other
people then that virus will spread
smiles spread in a group grumpy feeling
unhappy feeling spreads in a group I
will be a good example and this is how I
can help a lot of people I will work
hard with my meditation my yoga my study
and I would be an example of a person in
this short deadly life I will be a
shining light for other people
I'll be hope for other people I will be
a good person who treats other people
equally as well as I can and that's for
each other I will be a good example
with your friend good luck you know be
I'll see you again soon I'll take care
of you don't worry and then you can open
your eyes take a stretch